National Archives and Records Service Copies of Federal Documentation on Black Workers 5584
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
National Archives and Records Service Copies of Federal Documentation on Black Workers
1916- 1943
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
National Archives and Records Service
5584
15 cubic feet
15 linear ft.
Records (documents).
These are facsimile documents gathered by Professors James Gross and Cletus Daniel for their esearch project on Black Workers. These records were selected from many others and in each case by no means represent the complete series held by the National Archives. Researchers wishing to pursue further study in a particular series are advised to obtain the relevant series number (such numbers are stamped on the back of each document) and refer to it when attempting to locate the series at NARS. Use of this collection is restricted to term paper references for Cornell undergraduates until otherwise specified.
5667676
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, September 20, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, June 05, 2019
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5584 A: National Archives and Records Service Copies of Federal Documentation on Black Workers 5584 mf: National Archives and Records Service Copies of Federal Documentation on Black Workers on Microfilm
African Americans -- History -- Sources; United States. National Archives and Records Service.
5667676
- National Recovery Administration (Box 1)
  - National Recovery Administration. Labor Advisory Board (NRA-LAB), 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes 9 page mimeo entitled, "The NRA and the Negro Worker," by Gustov Peck; Correspondence re request of investigation into treatment and living and labor conditions of farm laborers in the Sugar Belt of Louisiana; Requests for changes in codes; re reasons for North and South wage differentials; re question of Negro representation on Advisory Board; re codes for lumber and timber industry, statement (10 pages) of Negro Industrial League concerning the affect of Negro labor
  - NRA-LAB - Subject File of "Negro Displacement" -, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Correspondence with Matthew F. Boyd, Assistant Labor Advisor of the Board re the displacement of Negroes under the NRA in various localities; 7 page mimeo "Conclusions from Survey in Alabama of the Effect of the Operations of the NRA Code on Negro Labor;" 6 page mimeo, "A Study of the Position of Negro Workers Under the National Industrial Recovery Act;" "The Subnormal Negro and the Subnormal Code."
  - NRA-LAB - Subject File - "Negro Labor" -, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Correspondence with Rose Schneiderman, member, Labor Advisory Board and others re Negro representative to be placed on the Board; wages of Negroes in various industries; discrimination against Negroes in unions
  - NRA-LAB - "Negro Labor" -, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Correspondence re the displacement of Negroes due to the payment of code wages and hours; "Statement of the Negro Industrial League concerning the Code of Fair Competition for the Cotton Textile Industry"
  - NRA-LAB - "Regional Differentials", 1933 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Correspondence re the wage differentials between Black and white laborers
  - NRA-LAB - "Southern" -, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Correspondence re skilled and unskilled labor in the south; 3 page mimeo "Objection to Minimum Wage Discrimination Against Negro Workers," by General Secretary of the National Consumer's League
  - NRA-LAB, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Correspondence re wage differentials (regional and racial); code definition of gin workers; request for exemptions under the code
  - NRA - General -, 1934-1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    7 page mimeo "Excerpts from the Statement of John P. Davis, Given at the Hearing on Employment Provisions in Codes of Fair Competition on February 2, 1935;" Differentials-geographic; several pages of testimony re strike situation at Packard Motor Company because of race issue
  - NRA - Report -, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes "Report of the Agriculture Committee of the Inter-Departmental Group Concerned with the Special Problem of Negroes, May 1934," 16 pages
  - NRA - Miscellaneous Minutes - (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes minutes of meetings of the Inter-Departmental Group concerned with the special problems of Negroes, March 2, 30, 1934; b) This section contains general correspondence of A.R. Forbush, Chief Correspondence Division, NRA (and others) filed in alphabetical order - Includes appeal letters and documents for economic relief re unfair conditions
- National Recovery Administration (Box 2)
  - A -, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Correspondence from Black and white individuals, organization, American Legion, AME Church, Mason Telegraph, to Franklin D. Roosevelt, General Hugh Johnson and NRA requesting emergency relief from economic conditions, racial discrimination, displacement of Black workers due to minimum wage, alleged code violation, general population, coal, railroad, cotton industry, and requesting appointment of Blacks to NRA-LAB. Replies by Forbush and other officials in the agency.
  - American Consolidated Trades Council -, 1926-1933 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Correspondence from Chicago Colored Plumbers Protective Association, predecessor to American Consolidated Trades Council, a Black building trades association, to United Association of Journeyman Plumbers and Steam Fitters. President John Coefield, Building Committee Provident Hospital and Training School; President M.J. McDonough, Building Trades Department, AFL; Chicago Federation of Labor; Frances Perkins, Secretary of Labor seeking end to racial discrimination in building trades with negative results.
  - B, 1932-1935 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Correspondence from Black clergy and the Baptist Minister's Conference of New York requesting FDR, General Johnson, NRA provide emergency relief from economic conditions, racial discrimination, displacement of Black workers due to increase minimum wage, alleged code violation, in general, domestics, building trades and requests for appointment of Blacks to the NRA-LAB.
  - C, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Correspondence with Senator Capper of Kansas and organizations such as the Churches of Christ, Citizens Taxpayer's Association, Coopers Curtain's Draperies and Linens, Urban League and NAACP of Kansas to General Johnson, FDR and NRA for emergency relief from adverse economic conditions, racial discrimination, wages displacement of Back workers due to increase in minimum wage, alleged code violation and for appointment of Black to NRA-LAB.
  - D, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Correspondence by worker in Charleston, S.C. regarding exploitation of white and Black workers by Planters Fertilizer Company through wage cuts of 35 and 50 percent despite rise of sale price and urging General Hugh Johnson to correct this situation; also from other individuals and organizations: Delta Sigma Theta Sorority, Dutchess County Department of Child Welfare, Dallas Negro Chamber of Commerce to FDR, General Hugh Johnson, NRA, requesting relief from economic conditions, displacement due to minimum wage increase, alleged codes of fair practices violations in steel, railroads, brick works, AFL, and for appointment of Blacks to LAB and Consumer Advisory Board.
  - E, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Correspondence from individuals and organizations, Urban League sponsored Emergency Advisory Council of Tampa, Trenton and Atlanta, relief from economic conditions, racial discriminations and for appointment of Black to NRA-LAB.
  - F, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Correspondence from individuals requesting relief from economic conditions; letter from merchant requesting investigation of unfair labor practices of planters and farmers in St. Mary's Parish, Louisiana for forced trade at employer owned stores, use of merchandise as wage substitute practice formerly used exclusively against Blacks, threatens independent merchants. Response as to legality of practice.
  - G, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    correspondence from individuals requesting relief from economic conditions; letter to General Hugh Johnson from Black steel worker and former policeman in Gary, Indiana, describes economic conditions, warning of communist.
  - H-I, 1933-1935 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Correspondence from individuals requesting relief from economic conditions; from organizations - Industrial Council of Los Angeles; Insurance Agents Relief Association of Baltimore; Interdenominational Ministerial Alliance of Kansas City and the Iroquois Democratic Club of Rochester.
  - J (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Correspondence from Joint Committee for National Recovery; Baptist clergyman; Congressman Oscar DePriest to FDR, General Hugh Johnson, NRA for relief from economic conditions and protesting dismissal of Black administrator, Mabel J. Byrd and payment of veterans benefits.
  - K, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Correspondence from individuals and organizations including Kansas State Association of Colored Women requesting relief from economic conditions.
  - L, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Correspondence from Laboring men's Protective Association to General Johnson and reply; cites racial discrimination and request for appointment of Black to NRA.
  - M, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Correspondence requesting relief from economic conditions in fertilizer, tobacco, laundry and cleaning, and agricultural industries
- National Recovery Administration (Box 3)
  - N, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Correspondence from individuals and organizations - National Association of Colored Women, National Council of World War Vets, Negro Industrial League, National Technical Association to FDR, General Johnson, NRA, citing economic conditions, racial discrimination in employment and wages, displacement of Black workers by whites, alleged code violations, requesting Federal intervention.
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), 1933-1934 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Correspondence re displacement of Negroes under NRA codes; 19 page mimeo, "NAACP, 1932, 23rd Annual Report;" requests for exemptions; 3 page telegram to President Roosevelt from Wilkins re discrimination with codes; requests for appointments of Blacks to NRA-LAB
  - National Consumers League, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Correspondence citing Black worker displacement by whites in Atlanta, Georgia area; also minimum wage, discrimination, exemptions of apprenticeships and unskilled laborers from Code of Fair Practice; for appointment of Black to NRA-LAB.
  - National Urban League, 1933-1934 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Correspondence to NRA and Frances Perkins supporting uni-level wage plans for establishment of Emergency Advisory Councils; to Sidney Hillman, Labor Advisory Board citing racial discrimination, Code of Fair Competition violation by Scripto Manufacturing Company of Atlanta, memo from the company explaining that due to Black worker inefficiency they are to be paid less than white workers, also warns of possible job displacement.
  - P, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Correspondence from individuals and Philadelphia Tribune citing economic conditions, racial discrimination in employment and wages displacement of Black workers, code violations, requesting Federal alleviation by General Johnson, NRA-LAB. (33-? Second date cut off)
  - Pullman Company, 1926-1933 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    U.S. Board of Mediation, case documents - Pullman Company vs. Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters - includes official statements; correspondence between A. Philip Randolph and others, forms, bulletins; 15 page letter from Randolph to E.F. Carry, President, Pullman Company detailing history of the Brotherhood (6/9/27); broadsides, clippings
  - Pullman Company, 1926-1933 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - R, 1933-1934 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Correspondence regarding economic conditions, racial and marital discrimination seeking relief through NRA
  - S, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Correspondence citing racial and economic conditions, list of demands from Steel and Metal Workers Industrial Union and letter from Secretary NRA Compliance Board, Columbus, Georgia, informing General Johnson of plans by National Chamber of Commerce to establish 25% of 30% wage differential of Black workers by whites. Request for paid administrator and/or inspector.
  - T, 1933-1935 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Correspondence re race discrimination within the industry codes; 18 page mimeo, "Tuskegees' Service in National Recovery;" and routine correspondence
  - U, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    routine
  - W, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    routine correspondence re discrimination
  - Y, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Correspondence re exploitation of household servants; from various YMCA organizations re discrimination in employment
- National Recovery Administration (Box 4)
  - Atlantic Coast Line, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Baltimore and Ohio, 1918-1919 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Boston and Albany, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Chesapeake and Ohio, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Chicago Lines, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Chicago Lines, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Chicago Lines, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Delaware, Lackawanna and Western, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Erie Railroad, 1918-1919 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Illinois Central, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Lehigh Valley, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    11a- Long Island Railroad (1919)
  - Louisville and Nashville, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Missouri Pacific, 1918-1919 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - New York Central Railroad, 1918-1919 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Pennsylvania Railroad, 1918-1919 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Pullman Company, 1919-1920 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Richmond, Fredericksburg Railroad, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Santa Fe Railroad, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    18a - Southern Pacific (1918)
  - Southern Railroad, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Union Pacific Railroad, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Washington Terminal, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Western Maryland Railroad, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- National Recovery Administration (Box 5)
  - Blue Crab Industry, 1934-1935 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    includes reports by the NRA Division of Research and Planning on the industry; Correspondence and memos, petitions re minimum wage for crab packers
  - Construction Industry, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    correspondence, reports, re reduction of minimum wage in this industry
  - Cotton Industry, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    correspondence, memos, reports, re classification of cotton gin workers, whether its industrial or agricultural
  - Tobacco Industry, 1931-1935 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    104 page manuscript. "Negro Labor in the Tobacco Industry in North Carolina" by C. Tineley Willis, 1931; correspondence re north/south wage differentials and miscellaneous, 1931-1935
  - Tobacco Industry, 1931-1935 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- National Recovery Administration (Box 6)
  - Auction and Loose Leaf Tobacco Warehouse Industry, NRA, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    December 28, 1933
  - China Clay Producing Industry, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    December 13, 1933 (incomplete)
  - Cigar Manufacturing Industry, NRA, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    January 10, 1934 (Incomplete) 3a- Cinders, Ashes and Scavenger Industry, NRA (December 6 1933)
  - Cotton Bale Covering Industry, NRA, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    April 23, 1934
  - Cotton Compress and Warehouse Industry, NRA, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    September 25, 1934
  - Cotton Garment Industry, NRA/NIRA, 1934-1935 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    October 9, 1934; March 9, 1934; May 9, 1935; May 17, 1935
  - Cotton Garment Industry, NRA/NIRA, 1934-1935 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Cotton Garment Industry, NRA/NIRA, 1934-1935 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Cotton Garment Industry, NRA/NIRA, 1934-1935 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Cotton Pickery Industry, NRA, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    January 8, 1935
  - Cotton Pickery Industry, NIRA, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    March 10, 1934
  - Cotton Seed Oil Refining Industry, NIRA, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    December 19, 1933
- National Recovery Administration (Box 7)
  - Cotton Textile Industry, NRA, 1933-1934 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    June 29, 1933, October 9, 1934
  - Cotton Textile Industry, NRA, 1933-1934 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Feed Manufacturing Industry, NRA, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    December 16. 1933 3a- Fertilizer Industry, NRA (June 6 1933)
  - Fishery Industry, NIRA, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    May 31 1934
  - Fresh Fruit and Vegetable Distributive Industry, NRA, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    January 8 1934
  - Hotel and Restaurant Industry, NRA, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    August 20, 1934 6a- Ice Industry, NRA (9/8/33)
  - Laundry Industry, NIRA 11/20 and 21/23 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Leaf Tobacco Industry, NRA, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    March 21 1934
  - Machined Waste Manufacturing Industry, NRA, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    March 21, 1934
  - Oyster Industry, NIRA, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    May 7, 1935
  - Oyster Shell Crushers Industry, NIRA, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    March 9, 1934
- National Recovery Administration (Box 8)
  - Paper Shell Pecan Industry, NIRA, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    October 23, 1933
  - Pecan Shelling Industry, NRA, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    November 27, 1933
  - Poultry (Live) Industry, NRA, 1934 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    December 8, 1934
  - Pulpwood Industry, NRA; NIRA, 1934-1935 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    NRA: June 5, 1934 NIRA: May 22, 1935
  - Raw Cotton Trade Industry, NRA, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    January 25, 1935
  - Raw Peanut Milling Industry, NRA, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    October 20, 1933 6a - Retail Merchandising Industry, NRA 7/2/1934 6b - Retail Solid Fuel Industry, NRA 11/13/33
  - Rubber Tire Manufacturing Industry, NRA, 1934 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    August 20, 1934 7a - Scrap, Iron, Non Ferrous Industry, NRA 10/2/1934
  - Soap and Glycerin Industry, NRA, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    October 5, 1933
  - Southern Rice Millers Industry, NRA, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    September 5 and 7 1933
  - Structural Clay Products Industry, NRA, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    August 23, 1933
  - Taxicab Industry, NIRA, 1934 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    February 13 1934
  - Vitrified Clay Sewer Pipe Manufacturing Industry, NRA, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    October 30, 1933 12a - Waste Material Industry, NRA, October 11, 1933
  - Miscellaneous Hearing - NIRA - Employment Provisions in Codes of Fair Competition, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    February 1, 2 1935
- U.S. Department of Labor. Lawrence A. Oxley. Subject Files. (Box 9)
  - Agriculture, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    United States government pamphlet on slums and housing with special emphasis on New York City and selected references on housing. Also speech on the Black farmer and the Agricultural Adjustment Act, 1936
  - Black Employment Problems by Specific Industries-, 1933-1935 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Correspondence re alleged discrimination against Blacks in staffing and employment in the steel, automobile, and textile industries. Proposed fair competition industry code for the laundry and cleaning service workers. Includes statistics for Ohio and Detroit industries and employees divided by race
  - Civilian Conservation Corps - Brown, Edgar -, 1934-1937 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Requests for information about Blacks and the New Deal. Favorable information to be used to swing Blacks to the Democratic political party.
  - Civilian Conservation Corps, 1934-1936 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    Correspondence re Black job applicants requesting aid to secure employment in the Civilian Conservation Corps
  - Commerce, Department of - Jones, Eugene Kinckle, 1935-1937 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Requests for information on Blacks in the New Deal
  - Conferences, 1939-1941 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    Correspondence re training and employment of Blacks for national defense industries in Saint Paul and Minneapolis. Employment problems of the Blacks in Trenton, NJ, Los Angeles; Wilmington, Indianapolis, Chicago, and Little Rock. Speech on the place of Blacks in the Employment Security Program in Illinois Speech on training needs and employment opportunity in the day workers and personal service fields. Proceedings of the second National Conference on the problems of the Blacks and Black Youth. Speech on the U.S. Employment Service and the Black job applicant.
  - Differentials - Racial and Wages -, 1934-1935 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    Correspondence re alleged discrimination against Blacks in staffing and employment. Reports on racial and wage differentials due to the fair competition industry codes of the NRA
  - Elevator Operators -, 1934-1935 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    Correspondence concerning alleged discrimination against Black elevator operators in the various federal buildings in Washington, DC
  - Employment Security -, 1941 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    Proceedings of the Institute on Routine documents
  - Farm Credit Administration, 1934-1936 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    Correspondence concerning the Farm Credit Administration programs available to Blacks including emergency relief and employment. Letters from Black job applicants requesting aid in securing employment
  - Federal Security Agency - Social Security Board, Maryland, 1941-1942 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    Information about Blacks in National Defense and Industry. Alleged racial discrimination in Maryland. Includes statistics on industry and employees. Describes attitudes towards Black employees.
- U.S. Department of Labor. Lawrence A. Oxley. Subject Files. (Box 10)
  - Federal Security Agency - Social Security Board, Region Seven -, 1941-1942 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Includes material on national defense training and employment for Blacks in various industries including aircraft, automobile, chemical, communications, construction, electrical, iron and steel, metal and shipbuilding in the south. Discrimination against Blacks by labor unions and employers. Majority of documents from the Seventh Regional Labor Supply Committee which monitors six southern states including Alabama, Florida, Georgia, Mississippi, South Carolina, and Tennessee. Includes reports and statistics.
  - Federal Security Agency - Social Security Board, Region Seven, 1941-1942 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Illinois Central Railroad - Killing of Black Firemen, 1933-1936 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    Newspaper and magazine articles describing the murders of Black railroad firemen by white railroad workers who wanted their jobs. Informal paper on immigrant unskilled construction labor and the formation of the International Hod Carriers, Building and Common Laborers Union of America
  - Interior, Department of - Conference of Youth Leaders, 1936 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    Routine documentation
  - Interior, Department of - Robert C. Weaver -, 1933-1937 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    Correspondence concerning discrimination against Blacks in a Federal Emergency Relief Administration project in Florida and in Public Works Administration Projects at Cleveland, Ohio; Atlantic City, New Jersey; Savannah and Atlanta, Georgia; Columbia, South Carolina; New Orleans, Louisiana; and Nashville, Tennessee. Agreements concerning the staffing of Black workers on Public Works Administration projects. Reports on wages paid to skilled, semi-skilled and un-skilled Black labor on these PWA projects. Report on the Tobacco Industry in North Carolina.
  - Interior, Department of - Office of Education -, 1933-1934 (Box 10, Folder 6)